<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The blessing of Moses on the tribe of Asher opened and applyed in a mystical and spiritual sense, to every saint, and servant of Christ in a sermon on Deut. 33.25 ... / by T. Beverley.</title>
            <author>Beverley, Thomas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1693</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 55 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A27583</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B2124</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R20407</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11771389</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11771389</idno>
            <idno type="VID">48870</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A27583)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 48870)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 808:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The blessing of Moses on the tribe of Asher opened and applyed in a mystical and spiritual sense, to every saint, and servant of Christ in a sermon on Deut. 33.25 ... / by T. Beverley.</title>
                  <author>Beverley, Thomas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.A. for John Harris ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1693.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
                  <note>Preached September 3, 1693.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Deuteronomy XXXIII, 25 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:48870:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:48870:1"/>
            <p>THE BLESSING OF MOSES ON THE <hi>Tribe of Aſher,</hi> Opened and Applyed: In the Myſtical and Spiritual Senſe, to every Saint and Servant of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>IN A SERMON ON</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Deut. 33. 25.</bibl> Thy Shooes ſhall be Iron and Braſs, and as thy Days, ſo ſhall thy ſtrength be.</q>
            <p>By <hi>T. BEVERLEY.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. A.</hi> for <hi>John Harris</hi> at the <hi>Harrow</hi> in the <hi>Poultrey.</hi> 1693.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:48870:2"/>
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p n="1">1. THE <hi>Revelation <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nvail'd:</hi> Or an Eſſay towards the Diſcovering, 1. When many Scripture Prophecies had their Accompliſhment, and turned into Hiſtory. 2. What are now Fulfilling. 3. What reſt ſtill to be Fulfilled, with a gueſs at the Time of them. With an Appendix, proving that <hi>Pagan Rome,</hi> was not <hi>Babylon, Rev.</hi> 17. And that the <hi>Jews</hi> ſſall be Converted. By <hi>Samu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el Petto</hi> of <hi>Sudbury</hi> in <hi>Suffolk.</hi> Price one ſhilling ſix pence.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A Faithfull Narrative of the Wonderfull and Extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Fits which Mr. <hi>Tho. Spatchet</hi> (late of <hi>Dunwich</hi> and <hi>Cookly</hi>) was under by Witchcraft: Or, a Myſterious Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in his even Unparallel'd Fits: With an Account of his firſt Falling into, Behaviour under, and (in Part) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance out of them. Wherein are ſeveral Remarkable Inſtances of the Gracious Effects of Fervent Prayer. The whole drawn up and written by <hi>Samuel Petto,</hi> Miniſter at <hi>Sudbury</hi> in <hi>Suffolk,</hi> who was an Eye-witneſs of a great Part. Price ſix Pence.</p>
            <p n="3">3. A Collction of modern Relations of <hi>Matter of fact,</hi> concerning <hi>Witches</hi> and <hi>Witchcraft</hi> upon the Perſons of Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. To which is prefixed a Meditation concerning the Mercy of God, in preſerving us from the Malice and Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of evil Angels. Written by the late Lord Chief Juſtice <hi>Hale,</hi> upon occaſion of a Tryal of ſeveral Witches before him. Part I. Price one Shilling.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Neceſſary Queſtions concerning <hi>Witches</hi> and <hi>Witchcraft</hi> briefly Anſwered. By the ſame Author. Price One Penny.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Mathematical Divinity:</hi> Or a plain Demonſtration from the Holy Scriptures, that the Times of this World were fore-appointed by the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant made with <hi>Abraham;</hi> and determined to be according to the Meaſure of the Age and Fulneſs of Chriſt. Kept Secret ſince the World began, but is now made plain upon Twelve Tables, in a Solar Calendar as familiar to the Underſtanding as a common Almanack. With a full Proof that this is the laſt Generation, which ſhall not paſs away till all things be Fulfilled, and the Gates of Righteouſneſs be opened. Being the Reſult of many years Study. By <hi>Elias Palmer.</hi> Price One Shilling.</p>
            <p>All Printed for <hi>John Harris</hi> at the <hi>Harrow</hi> in the <hi>Poultrey.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:48870:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>THIS plain and ſhort Diſcourſe holds out the spiritual ſtrength and ſupport of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, flowing from the Grace of God in Jeſus Chriſt, and the mighty Efficacies of the Holy Spirit, amidſt the <hi>Stony Places,</hi> the roughneſſes and ſharpneſſes of inward and outward Tryals and Temptations; as alſo the moſt Compaſſionate proportionings of that ſtrength to the Exigencies and Neceſſities of each Day of Tryal, and to the utmoſt length of Time, and through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Eternity. In the Expreſſion and Repreſentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of which, the admirable Elegancy and Significancy of the words uſed by the Bleſſed Spirit in this Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, offer the moſt lively Images and Notions: But the inward Efficacy and Power are alone from that Bleſſed Spirit that breathed them.</p>
            <p>Let us bow our Knees therefore to the Father of Glory, that he would grant us, according to the Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of his Glory, to be thus ſtrengthened, to have Feet
<pb facs="tcp:48870:3"/> thus ſhod with the preparation of the Goſpel of peace. And that as our Times are in his Hand, ſo that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his hand we may commend our Spirits; that he, as the Lord God of Truth would redeem us, and that we may Redeem and Buy off Time from all the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advantages and Encumbrances of it, by ſtrength given from him according to the Day; till all Time is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected and Conſummate in the Fulneſs of Times, or of All Times in the Kingdom of Chriſt, and of Eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>T. B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>The <hi>Reader</hi> is deſir'd to Accept this Diſcourſe, as ſpoken (and ſo deſired now) in the greateſt Plainneſs, Freedom, and Famili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arity of Expreſſion, for every Apprehenſion, to every ones Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and to correct the Errors of the firſt Sheet, eſpecially oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion'd through Diſtance from the Preſs.</head>
            <list>
               <item>PAge 3. l. 3. for <hi>Force</hi> r. <hi>Diſplay.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>p. 4. l. 22. for <hi>herein</hi> r. <hi>Here, in.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>p. 7. l. 7. for <hi>wherein</hi> r. <hi>ſtands.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>l. 14. for <hi>the</hi> r. <hi>unto.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>l. 26. for <hi>though there be</hi> r. <hi>For there is.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>l. 30. for <hi>amongſt</hi> r. <hi>amidſt.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>P. 8. l. 9. after <hi>God</hi> r. <hi>Theſe.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>P. 20. l. 22. after <hi>end</hi> r. <hi>For.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:48870:3"/>
            <head>A SERMON Preached <hi>Septemb.</hi> 3. 1693.</head>
            <head type="sub">On</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>DEUT. XXXIII. 25.</bibl>
                  <p>Thy Shooes ſhall be Iron and Braſs; and as thy Dayes, ſo ſhall thy Strength be.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>I Have undertaken by the Aſſiſtance of God, to ſpeak to you on this Text; which was the Bleſſing of <hi>Moſes</hi> the Man of God, the Servant of God, particularly upon <hi>Aſher,</hi> the Tribe of <hi>Aſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the ſenſe of it is Prophetical: And ſo it Requires the Diligent Attendance, and Enquiry of our Thoughts; that we may be led into the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual and Divine ſenſes and meaning of it. If you look into the Chapter, you will find, that it is the Bleſſing, wherewith <hi>Moſes</hi> the Man of God, Bleſſed the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> before his Death.</p>
            <p>And if you ſhall ſay, How may this Concern us?</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:48870:4"/>
            <p>It is to be conſidered in Anſwer: That whatſover hath been ſpoken of Old, by the ſervants of God, in Relation to <hi>Iſrael</hi> in General; <hi>Iſrael,</hi> I ſay, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered Naturally, in the Natural Stock and Race, that proceeded from <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> the very ſame, every thing ſhall have its Courſe, ſhall have its Complement, ſhall have its fulfilling in the Spiritual <hi>Iſrael;</hi> in all thoſe that are the <hi>Iſrael</hi> of God. For, as the Apoſtle ſaith to the <hi>Galatians,</hi> Chap. 4. 26. <hi>The Jeruſalem which is above, is the Mother of us all:</hi> ſo that we are all within what was ſpoken of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and of the Tribes of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael;</hi> if we are indeed the <hi>Iſrael</hi> of God: As he uſes the very ſame Expreſſion: <hi>Peace be upon you, and mercy, and upon the Iſrael of God.</hi> This very Conſideration ought to Engage us into the Enquiry after Divine Truths, with relation to the natural <hi>Iſrael. Gal.</hi> 6. 6. <hi>As many as walk according to this Rule, Peace be on them, and Mercy, and upon the Iſrael of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo, what was ſpoken Particularly to the Tribes, concerned in ſome regard or other, and ſhall Run down upon all the ſervants of God, who are all thoſe that make up the Twelve Tribes of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> As we find in the <hi>Revelation,</hi> Chap. 7. which Viſion, I am very well Aſſured (notwithſtanding ſome indeed would ſo Literally Interpret it) is to be underſtood of ſpiritual <hi>Iſrael. And I heard the number of them which were ſealed, of every one of the Tribes,</hi> or of <hi>all</hi> the <hi>Tribes of Iſrael.</hi> Ver. 4. I ſay, it concerns the ſpiritual <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that ſhall keep cloſe to God, in the Great Antichriſtian Apoſtacy. And therefore in Relation to them, ſhall all the Songs, and Bleſſings
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:48870:4"/> that were upon <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and the Tribes of it, come again (as I may ſo ſpeak with Reverence) into Force; they ſhall have their full Effect upon all the Servants of God. It is ſaid <hi>Rev.</hi> 15. Ver. 3. <hi>They ſung the Song of Moſes the ſervant of God.</hi> The Song of <hi>Moſes</hi> the Servant of God, is to have its courſe again in theſe Witneſſes of the Lamb. And ſo the Bleſſing of every one of the Tribes, and the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of <hi>Aſher,</hi> ſhall have its Courſe, ſhall have its full Complement and Iſſue, and fullneſs, in all the People and Servants of God; even this very Text that I have now read to you, <hi>Thy ſhooes ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l be Iron and Braſs; and as thy days, ſo ſhall thy ſtrength be.</hi> We find therefore <hi>Rev.</hi> 21. that as there was the Names of the <hi>Apoſtles of the Lamb,</hi> upon the <hi>twelve foundations;</hi> ſo there was alſo <hi>twelve Gates,</hi> and they had upon them the <hi>Names of the twelve Tribes of the Children of Iſrael,</hi> Verſe 12.</p>
            <p>This therefore I have ſpoken by way of Preface, that you may not think this great Text of Scripture is nothing to you, that it is nothing to us: But that we may know, that we have our ſhare and our Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt in it, and it ſhall be fulfilled in and upon us, if we are the Servants of God.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <p>I come therefore to a more Particular Conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on at this time, of <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Bleſſing on <hi>Aſher.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here are Two great Branches of this Text. <hi>Thy Shooes ſhall be Iron and Braſs, and as thy days, ſo ſhall thy ſtrength be. Aſher</hi> indeed was one of the Sons of <hi>Jacob</hi> by the Hand-maid of <hi>Leah:</hi> His Name imports Bleſſing; it was given to him by the Special Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God, that he as the Father of one of the Tribes
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:48870:5"/> of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> might bear the Memorial of that Bleſſing, and Bleſſedneſs enſtated on the Spiritual Seed of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> by God through him in whom all the Families of the Earth are Bleſſed; and in Relation to whom his Mother accounted her ſelf Bleſſed, in bearing a Son who ſhould be the Father of one of the Tribes of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and bear the Type of Bleſſedneſs for all the <hi>Iſrael</hi> of God enſtated upon it by the God of <hi>Jacob,</hi> therefore ſhe called his Name <hi>Aſher;</hi> that is to ſay, <hi>Bleſſed.</hi> And ſaith <hi>Moſes, Thy ſhoes ſhall be Iron and Braſs, and as thy days, ſo ſhall thy ſtrength be.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Interpreters give the very literal Senſe to be this: That <hi>Aſher</hi> had the Portion, the Lot in the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> that was a Land of <hi>Mines,</hi> of <hi>Mines</hi> of Iron and Braſs; and that relating to this, <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaid, <hi>Thy ſhooes ſhall be Iron and Braſs:</hi> Thou ſhalt be (as it were) ſhod with Iron and Braſs; and throughout, thy Day ſhall be the ſtrength of Iron and Braſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Job</hi> ſaid, <hi>Is my ſtrength the ſtrength of braſs?</hi> Now herein <hi>Aſher</hi> is the Promiſe to the Servants of God, that their Shooes ſhall be Iron and Braſs, and their Day ſhall have a Proportion of ſtrength, every way fitted and ſuited to it.</p>
               <p>And therefore I would give you the Spiritual ſenſe of theſe Words; and I would give it you out of Scripture, that you may find, that all Scripture has a Relation and a ſtrong Connection, one part of it with another. <hi>Eph.</hi> 6. 15. ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Having your feet ſhod with the preparation of the Goſpel of peace.</hi>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:48870:5"/> Having an Aſſurance of the great Glory of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel of Peace, that ſhall break out upon you: And having a Preparation upon your ſelves, a readineſs to enter into the Glory, and into the Bleſſedneſs of that State; <hi>Having your feet ſhod with the preparation of the Goſpel of peace,</hi> You ſhall find your Feet in a Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual ſenſe ſhod with Iron and Braſs.</p>
               <p>When any of us have our Feet ſhod with the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration of the Goſpel of peace, then are our Shooes Iron and Braſs, then ſhall we be ready and able to tread upon Temptation and to overcome: To riſe up above the Power of Sin and Death, and to trample them under our Feet. Then ſhall we be enabled to tread upon the Lyon and the Scorpion, and upon the very <hi>power of the Enemy.</hi> As the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſpeaks, <hi>Rom.</hi> 16. 20. <hi>The God of peace ſhall bruiſe Satan under your feet ſhortly:</hi> This is becauſe their <hi>feet</hi> are <hi>ſhod with the preparation of the Goſpel of peace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So this is the Promiſe in the Spiritual part of it, and it ſhall never ceaſe: This Promiſe ſhall have its Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration upon all the Servants of God; every one of them comes under the Bleſſing of every one of theſe Tribes; ſo this Bleſſing ſhall be accompliſhed and ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled in them. <hi>Their ſhooes ſhall be Iron and Braſs;</hi> and <hi>according to their day,</hi> ſo <hi>ſhall their ſtrength be;</hi> that is, conſider ſtrength how you will, as I ſhall preſently particularize to you. As their <hi>days,</hi> ſo ſhall their <hi>ſtrength</hi> be.</p>
               <p>And thus having Opened to you the General Scope and Senſe of the Text, I ſhall lay down this Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:48870:6"/>
                  <hi>That it is an Aſſured Bleſſing, a Bleſſing that is ſo conferr'd, ſo ſettled, ſo Enſtated upon every Servant of God, as he is of the Tribes of the Children of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael; as he is one of the twelve Tribes, as he is one in every one of the Twelve Tribes, and ſo in</hi> Aſher: <hi>He ſhall have a Strength for the Day, overcoming all the power of the Enemy: For this is the Extenſion and Largeneſs of Spirituality; Every one in theſe Twelve Tribes in a Spiritual ſenſe, have a ſhare in every Bleſſing in a Spiritual ſenſe: And therefore up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on every Servant of God this Bleſſing is enſtated and ſettled, that their</hi> Shooes ſhall be of Iron and Braſs; <hi>their Feet ſhall be ſhod with the preparation of the Goſpel of peace: and into whatſoever Encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and Combat they come, as their</hi> Day <hi>is, ſo ſhall</hi> their ſtrength be; <hi>even to the uttermoſt State of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity it ſelf.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſhall therefore Propoſe to you, in the firſt Place, To open and to enlarge upon the Particulars of this Part, that their <hi>Shooes ſhall be Iron and Braſs:</hi> And then in the ſecond Place to open and enlarge upon that, That as <hi>their day is, ſo ſhall their ſtrength be:</hi> And then in the third place, I ſhall give you the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Reaſons for Aſſerting it, the Demonſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons from Scripture of it: And in the fourth place, I ſhall lead you into the Proſpect (as <hi>Moſes</hi> gat up to take a view of all the Poſſeſſion of the Children of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi>) of all the great Glory of the Kingdom of Chriſt, that is aimed at in all theſe Bleſſings, and principally deſigned, and conclude with the Application of it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>I begin with the Firſt: <hi>Thy Shooes ſhall be Iron and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:48870:6"/> Braſs;</hi> that is, Thou ſhalt tread upon any thing that ſtands in thy way, and thou ſhalt trample it down; thou ſhalt ſubdue it through the Power of Grace.</p>
               <p>And this I ſhall open to you in theſe three or four Particulars, wherein the ſtrength of the Servants of God, that are every one as every one of the Tribes of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and as this Tribe of <hi>Aſher;</hi> wherein,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> It ſhall be ſhew'd, in trampling upon the <hi>Power of Sin,</hi> in the Guilt of it; the treading down of the Power of Sin in the Guilt of it; that great Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that Satan has againſt the Servants of God in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the guilt that is upon them; the Accuſations wherewith he would even give them not only the Foil, but the Fall, the Ruine and Deſtruction. He thinks to ſet upon them, and to undermine them, to <hi>overthrow their going,</hi> as the Expreſſion of <hi>David</hi> is: He thinks to overthrow their going in this great point, that they are Sinners, and lyable to Wrath, and Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Condemnation. Now to be able to tread upon the Baſilisk, and the Serpent in this matter; to be able to tread upon his Head, requires indeed <hi>Feet ſhod with the preparation of the Goſpel of peace;</hi> that is indeed with the Satisfaction, with the Blood, and with the Death and Reſurrection and Interceſſion of our Lord Jeſus: And who is able to do that, to lay faſt hold upon the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt? though there be nothing ſo deadly as to tread among the Scorpions of our own Sins, the Cry of which is againſt us like the Blood of <hi>Abel:</hi> And therefore I ſay, to walk amongſt theſe, it is to walk indeed amongſt the Gates of Death; to be treading upon Death it ſelf, that is ready to riſe
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:48870:7"/> up againſt us. Our <hi>footſteps</hi> are <hi>hunted,</hi> as the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of the Pſalmiſt is: Hunted by this great Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſer of the Brethren; he follows us into our moſt private Retirements, into our Thoughts as far as he can divine at them; our Cloſets, our whole Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, our Company; our being at home, our being abroad; our being in Buſineſs, our being in Diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſement; our being in our Trade, our being in the Duties of Holineſs, and drawing nigh to God; are all watch'd by him; he hunts our ſteps through all theſe, and there are Snares laid for us. As it was the ſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagem of thoſe Times in War, that they drove ſharp ſtakes of Iron in the way of thoſe that were coming out againſt them; they had need then be ſhod with <hi>Iron</hi> and <hi>Braſs,</hi> that they might tread upon thoſe Spikes of Iron. Now ſo are the Accuſations of Satan ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing from our Guilt, and when they are armed with the Juſtice of God, and the Holineſs and Purity of his Law, O! what ſhall we do if we are not ſhod with <hi>Iron</hi> and <hi>Braſs?</hi> If we have not the Aſſurance of the Love of God in Jeſus Chriſt? As the Apoſtle ſpeaks, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. ſaith he, <hi>We are more than Conquerors through him that loved us. For I am perſwaded, that neither death, nor life, nor Angels, nor principalities, nor powers, nor things preſent, nor things to come; nor height, nor depth, nor any other Creature ſhall be able to ſeparate us from the love of God, which is in Chriſt Jeſus our Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here are the things that we are to walk amongſt, and to tread amongſt: Now if we have not Shooes of <hi>Iron</hi> and <hi>Braſs,</hi> how ſhall we be able to walk amongſt theſe? But through the Love of God in Jeſus Chriſt, we ſhall be in all theſe things <hi>more than Conquerours.</hi>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:48870:7"/> O! therefore, let us look to this, to have the Feet of our Conſciences (if I may ſo expreſs it) to have them ſhod with <hi>Iron</hi> and <hi>Braſs,</hi> with that certain defence of the Blood of Jeſus: And then as Jeſus Chriſt ſpeaks of himſelf in that Prophecy of <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> wherein he repreſents himſelf coming out againſt his Adverſaries; ſaith he, in <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 63. 3. <hi>I have trodeen the Wine preſs alone, and of the people there was none with me: I will tread them in mine anger, and trample them in my fury; and their blood ſhall be ſprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kled upon my Garment, and I will ſtain all my Rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> Something like this every Saint may ſay.</p>
               <p>Chriſt will have a Glorious Victory upon all his Enemies, whoever, and of what kind ſoever they are. <hi>Who is he that will condemn me,</hi> ſaith he in another place. <hi>He is near that juſtifieth me: And therefore I have ſet my face like a flint; and I know I ſhall not be aſhamed, I ſhall not be confounded.</hi> When we have this Armour of Proof, this Armour of the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt on the right Hand, and on the left, we ſhall not be diſcouraged, till we have obtained the Victory over all: For he is Mighty that is in us, and that hath undertaken for us, and that hath provided us this great defence againſt the Guilt of Sin, againſt the Wrath of God, againſt all, that the Accuſer of our Souls can raiſe up againſt us.</p>
               <p>In the <hi>Second</hi> Place: Our Feet ſhall be ſhod with <hi>Iron</hi> and <hi>Braſs,</hi> in regard of all the <hi>Temptations to Sin,</hi> and from the World. However, they may be very great, and very ſharp; what by way of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticement
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:48870:8"/> to Pleaſure, or what by way of Terror in ſuffering; whatſoever is the Method, and the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and the Stratagem of this great Enemy of our Souls, we ſhall be able (having our Feet ſhod with <hi>Iron</hi> and <hi>Braſs</hi>) to overcome him, having a holy Reſolution, a holy Purpoſe of Soul; yea, though we may <hi>fall,</hi> yet we <hi>ſhall riſe again.</hi> He will keep us in all our Ways. And this Defence, theſe Shooes, theſe War like Boots (as the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſometimes ſpeaks of) theſe ſhall defend us a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all the Power of Temptations: We ſhould therefore go out in that ſtrength of the Lord our God; we ſhould go out in that Armour of Jeſus Chriſt, that <hi>Armour of God,</hi> as the Apoſtle calls it, in the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> and perſwades every one that they would take care to be Armed (as we ſay) <hi>Cap-a-pe,</hi> from Head to Foot throughout; that we ſhould be Armed with the <hi>whole Armour of God,</hi> Epheſ. 6. 11. <hi>That ye may be able to ſtand againſt the wiles of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil: For we wreſtle not againſt fleſh and blood, but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt principalities, againſt powers, againſt the Rulers of the darkneſs of this World, againſt ſpiritual wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in high places. Wherefore take unto you the whole Armour of God, that ye may be able to withſtand in the evil day, and having done all to ſtand.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O! if we did but find that we are ſhod with the <hi>preparation of the Goſpel of peace,</hi> this <hi>Iron</hi> and <hi>Braſs,</hi> we ſhould be able to tread down all the Temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that come to draw us off from God, and to Sin; we ſhould tread them as the Mire of the ſtreet, we ſhould never leave threſhing, and purſuing of them; <hi>Threſhing</hi> of them, as the Scripture expreſſion is:
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:48870:8"/> 
                  <hi>Ariſe, and threſh, O Daughter of Zion, for I will make thy horns Iron, and thy hoofs Braſs: Ariſe therefore, and threſh:</hi> So we ſhould ariſe, and threſh all the Power of Temptation that comes againſt us. O! how mighty ſhould we be in the ſtrength of God! If we conſider that great Love of God in Jeſus Chriſt, who can ſin againſt him? That great Love of Chriſt that conſtrains us: If we had the Power of dying to Sin, and of living in Newneſs of Life, through the <hi>Reſurrection of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle admirably expreſſes it, in the firſt Epiſtle of <hi>John,</hi> 5 Chapter, 4 <hi>Ver.</hi> ſaith he, <hi>Whatſoever is born of God, overcometh the World; and this is the Victory that overcometh the World, even our Faith. Who is he that overcometh the World, but he that believeth that Jeſus is the Son of God?</hi> Let us therefore lay hold upon the Arguments of the Goſpel, upon the Strength and Power of Jeſus Chriſt, in the Faith of his great undertaking: In that Faith let us go out and Conquer, let us go out and prevail. O! how would it raiſe us above this World, above the fears of it, above the delights of it, above the pleaſures of it! if we had but the Power of this Faith, if we had but this Victory of Faith in us, and upon us.</p>
               <p>In the <hi>Third</hi> Place, it would enable us to tread even upon <hi>Death</hi> it ſelf; upon all the Afflictions that are in our way to Heaven, and upon that King of Terrors, Death it ſelf: For, though indeed we ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend Death to be nothing but a Privation of Life in the General; yet we know as we are Chriſtians, it is an Inlet into Eternity: Even Nature ſtarts at it, as
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:48870:9"/> it is a Ceſſation, and putting an end to the life and motion, and action wherein we are converſant now; it looks much more dreadful to us, as it opens into Eternity. But if we were but ſhod with <hi>Iron</hi> and <hi>Braſs,</hi> we ſhould find theſe Shooes of Iron and Braſs would carry us through, and we ſhould be able to tread even upon the ſharpneſs of Death, and the Grave; we ſhould find the great Power of Jeſus Chriſt enabling of us, becauſe he has overcome Death: Even as he has overcome the World, ſo he has overcome Death. We ſhould never leave trying and proving this Armour of God upon the Feet of our Souls, till we find that we can walk even upon Graves, and upon our own Graves; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Tombs, and not be affrighted when we find we are carried thrô and thrô, and that we ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter and tread down as we go. We ſhould, I ſay, not only come and die when we muſt die, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore-hand we ſhould be armed at theſe very points; we ſhould find our Shooes herein to be of Iron and Braſs. Obſerve how triumphant <hi>David</hi> ſpeaks in the <hi>23d. Pſalm, Yea, though I walk through the Valley of the ſhadow of death:</hi> Where I don't know what may lye in my way, what may riſe up againſt me; I do not know what are the Secrets, what Ambuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cades there are in the Valley of Death; I don't know what Powers are appointed and prepared to Deſtroy. <hi>Yea,</hi> (in the <hi>4th.</hi> Verſe) <hi>though I walk through the Valley of the ſhadow of Death, I will fear no evil, for thou art with me,</hi> &amp;c. This would bear us through, and carry us with great Reſolution, and with undauntedneſs of Courage: For, the great ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:48870:9"/> of our Action (you know, in Scripture) is very much in our <hi>feet,</hi> in our <hi>walking.</hi> Now there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, to have our Feet thus ſhod, it would enable us to get up above theſe things; to be aloft over the things that are ſo dreadful and terrible to Fleſh and Blood. <hi>Hab.</hi> 3. 9. <hi>The Lord is my ſtrength, and he will make my feet like Hinds feet, and he will make me to walk upon mine high places:</hi> And therefore I can ſing, I can ſet a Song <hi>to the Chief Singer on my ſtringed Inſtruments.</hi> Becauſe I have ſuch an Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, ſuch an Elevation and Exultation of Soul in the Lord, <hi>I will rejoyce in the Lord,</hi> (Ver. 18.) <hi>and glory in the God of my Salvation, although the Fig-tree ſhall not bloſſom,</hi> &amp;c. Although there be no outward appearance of Good. O how timerous, how Cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardly are we, how ready to be affrighted at any appearance of Death! that in all our Diſcourſe we cannot endure the thing <hi>Dying:</hi> But were our Shooes but of <hi>Iron</hi> and <hi>Braſs,</hi> it would be eaſie, the way would be plain before us, we ſhould be able to ſtrike through every thing, and to the overcoming of it. And then</p>
               <p>In the Laſt place, Our Shooes being of <hi>Iron</hi> and <hi>Braſs,</hi> we ſhall be born up even when we have paſs'd out of the Body: For, though indeed we do not know the things that are beyond Death, none have come back to give us an Account, how it is with Spirits when they have left the Body: I ſay, none have come to give us Account; only the Word of God, that aſſures us, and tells us, that we ſhall be upon Precipices, when we go out of the World,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:48870:10"/> if we are not apprehended by Chriſt. Though un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly Satan hath way-laid the way of Spirits going out of the Body, with all the Incumberances he can poſſibly. As I told you before, it was the method of former times in War, they took care to lay whatever could incommode their Enemies Feet, with Stakes of Iron and Braſs, that might make the paſſage very difficult. So undoubtedly, that loſt and undone Spirit, that Envious Spirit, that great Adverſary of Souls, does whatever he can do to way-lay Spirits going out of the Body, and enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into the State of Eternity, and going up to the Throne of God, and the Throne of Chriſt, he does whatever he can do; but theſe Shooes of <hi>Iron</hi> and <hi>Braſs</hi> ſhall carry us through. Jeſus Chriſt himſelf hath taken care to remove him out of the way, ſo far as is neceſſary: and the great Action of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of a Saint going upo to Chriſt, and going up to God, it ſhall be ſuſtained and maintained by him, and he will arm us wherein ſoever we lye open to Diſadvantage, and to Danger: There will Chriſt more peculiarly provide; for I make no doubt, there is no one ſingle motion of the Spirits of Saints, but Chriſt hath ſo guarded, and ſo taken care of, as that very motion that we read of, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12. 7. The <hi>Duſt returning to the Earth as it was, and the Spirit to God that gave it.</hi> Now, what are (as I ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) the Ambuſcades? What are the ſecret Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of the way (as we ſpeak in Terms of War) lining all the Avenues of the way we know not? Satan hath lined them all with what may utterly ſpoil and deterr our motion up to God.</p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:48870:10"/>
               <p>But Jeſus Chriſt having firſt armed us with <hi>Shooes of Iron and Braſs,</hi> he himſelf will be found in the way, and he'll ſuſtain our paſſage, and cover our paſſage, and bear up all our motions unto God.</p>
               <p>And ſo I have opened the firſt of the great Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of the Bleſſedneſs that <hi>Moſes</hi> expreſſes of <hi>Aſher; Thy Shooes ſhall be Iron and Braſs:</hi> Of which, all the Mines that were in the Lot of <hi>Aſher,</hi> in that part of his poſſeſſion, they were but Types to ſet out this Almighty Power, this Almighty ſtrength of God unto Salvation.</p>
               <p>And therefore I ſhall cloſe this Head of Diſcourſe with that in the <hi>4th.</hi> Chapter of the Epiſtle to the <hi>Philippians,</hi> 7th. Verſe, ſaith he, <hi>The Peace of God which paſſeth all underſtanding.</hi> As he calls him <hi>the God of peace,</hi> Rom. 16. ſo here, <hi>The Peace of God which paſſeth all underſtanding, ſhall keep your hearts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is an Expreſſion either taken from a Guard of a City, or about the Perſon of any one. He ſhall keep (as under Guard and Defence) <hi>your Hearts and Minds through Chriſt Jeſus;</hi> a Peace that <hi>paſſes all underſtanding.</hi> O therefore, that we were but more acquainted, that we had but more of the Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this Glorious Chriſtianity, of this real Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and Power of it! We are too much Strangers to it, and averſe. We converſe more in the Forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, than in theſe mighty Powers and Principles of it! O how ſhould we try our ſelves, and put our
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:48870:11"/> ſelves by the Thoughts and Conſideration of Danger beforehand, to find out theſe <hi>Shooes of Iron and Braſs,</hi> the Neceſſity of them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>I come to the Second, which is a very great Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion: <hi>As thy Days, ſo ſhall thy ſtrength be.</hi> I know ſome tranſlate the word, ſignifying <hi>ſtrength,</hi> to this ſenſe; <hi>As thy Days, ſo ſhall thy</hi> Fame <hi>be:</hi> But this is rejected by the moſt Judicious Jewiſh, as other Interpreters; ſo I would open it to you in theſe following Particulars, that you may know what is the Importance of it: <hi>As thy Day,</hi> or, as <hi>thy Days, ſo ſhall thy Strength be.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the firſt place it ſignifies, That at any time when God ſees fit to bring us within the encounter of Danger, then he will take care by a peculiar Preſence, by a peculiar undertaking for us, by a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar Furniture, and preſent Suggeſtion, that we ſhall be carried through. In that Hour ſhall be <hi>gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven a Mouth,</hi> and ſo a <hi>Strength,</hi> the Adverſary ſhall not be able to reſiſt; for he knows what the <hi>Day</hi> is, and he will accordingly provide, he will give a proportion of ſtrength according unto that: He knows what kind of Day it is, what Ingredients it has, what kind of Temperature, how every thing ſhall fall out: Now ſaith God, and ſaith our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, I muſt conſider what a Day ſuch a Servant of mine is to come under, and what he is to undergo; I muſt therefore take care that he has a ſtrength proportionable, that he have a ſtrength ſuitable to it. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27. 1. ſaith <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:48870:11"/> The Lord is my Light, and my Salvation, whom ſhall I fear? The Lord is the ſtrength of my life, of whom ſhall I be afraid? When the wicked, even mine enemies and my foes came upon me to eat up my fleſh, they ſtumbled and fell. Though an Hoſt ſhould encamp againſt me, my heart ſhall not fear; though War ſhould riſe againſt me, in this will I be confident.</hi> Here is the great Aſſurance of the Servants of God, that let the Day be as dark, let the Day be as Critical a Day as can be, let it be a Day of the greateſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion, yet he that hath an Infinity of ſtrength, and that knows the Day to every particular Action of it, he will take care that there ſhall be a Furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and Proviſion of ſtrength ſuitable to it.</p>
               <p>And though you may ſay, (for ſo you may Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject) Aye, but do not oftentimes the Servants of God ſtumble and fall? Have they not great Falls and great Defeats, as it were?</p>
               <p>It is true, it may be ſo; even as the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in that of <hi>Ai,</hi> when the <hi>Accurſed thing</hi> was taken by <hi>Achan:</hi> But there ſhall be no reſt of things, till God hath reclaimed, and brought them back: He'll never leave, till he hath brought them back again: he'll bring a freſh ſtrength, he'll rally their force again, and as their <hi>Day is, ſo ſhall their ſtrength be:</hi> For he hath ſet down and counted what is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to come againſt the ſtrength, againſt the Power of ſuch a Day, and he will be ſure to take care in it. <hi>Deut.</hi> 33. 26. <hi>There is none like unto the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:48870:12"/> God of Jeſurun, who rideth upon the Heaven in thy help, and in his excellency on the Sky; the Eternal God is thy Refuge, and underneath are the everlaſting Arms, and he ſhall thruſt out the Enemy from before thee, and ſhall ſay, Deſtroy them. Iſrael ſhall dwell alone in ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and none to trouble him.</hi> Verſe 28, 29. <hi>Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py art thou, O Iſrael, who is like unto thee, O peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſaved by the Lord, the ſhield of thy help, and who is the Sword of thy Excellency! and thine Enemies ſhall be found Lyars unto thee, and thou ſhalt tread upon their high places.</hi> O! how great is the Aſſurance that God here gives! therefore, <hi>As thy Day, ſo ſhall thy ſtrength be. They prevented me in the day of my Calamity,</hi> (ſaith <hi>David) but the Lord was my ſtay.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the Second Place, it ſignifies this, That to the <hi>length of days,</hi> I ſay, that to <hi>the longeſt of days,</hi> that God has allotted to any of his Servants, <hi>ſo ſhall their ſtrength be.</hi> To the length of Days; if God hath determined to any of his Servants a ſhort Life, that a great deal of Life may be gathered up into a little Time: <hi>As is their day, ſo ſhall their ſtrength be;</hi> that is, they ſhall find a proportion of ſtrength, to the ſhortneſs of that State and Condition wherein they ſhall be in the World. Thus you find in the <hi>5th.</hi> Chapter of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> concerning <hi>Enoch,</hi> he was the ſhorteſt Liver of all thoſe Patriarchs before the Flood. <hi>And</hi> (in the <hi>22d.</hi> Verſe) <hi>Enoch walked with God after he begat Methuſelah three hundred years, and begat Sons and Daughters: and all his days were but three hundred ſixty and five years.</hi> A very ſhort time of Life, in compariſon of the reſt: but he Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banded
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:48870:12"/> that time, as was his Day, ſo was his Strength; he walked at a high rate with God, he walked a great way in a little time, he aſcended high in his Walk with God; <hi>And he was not, for God took him.</hi> So according to the Day, according to the length of his Day, ſo was his ſtrength: I ſay, he lived but a ſhort time in the World, but he did a great deal of Work in that ſhort time; his Heart was mightily lifted up in the ways of God.</p>
               <p>Again, On the other ſide, if God hath deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined a long Time for his Servants: <hi>As their Days, ſo ſhall their Strength be,</hi> even unto Old Age, and the hoary head, He is He that will bear them up. Therefore we ſhould not be afraid we ſhall forſake God at Laſt; God will not leave us, even in the Oldeſt Time of Life: For, God is exceeding careful of his own Honour in this Regard: I ſay he is Exceeding in his Care herein: <hi>Pſalm</hi> 92. 12, 13. <hi>The Righteous ſhall flouriſh like the Palm-tree; he ſhall grow like the Cedar in Lebanon. Thoſe that be planted in the houſe of the Lord, ſhall flouriſh in the Courts of our God. They ſhall ſtill bring forth Fruit in Old Age; they ſhall be fat and flouriſhing: To ſhew that the Lord is upright: he is my Rock, and there is no unrighteouſneſs in him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>God is carefull in this; It ſhall not be ſaid, That there is any Unrighteouſneſs in Him; It ſhall not be ſaid, He left any of his Servants in their Old Age, He was weary of them in their Old Age: But they ſhall flouriſh like the Palm-tree;
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:48870:13"/> and they ſhall be fat and flouriſhing. For, the Grace of God is able to run a Line Parallel with the longeſt of any of our Lives; and his Grace ſhall be ſufficient for us, even to the very laſt, and in the very end of Days: As I have already ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to you.</p>
               <p>But then there is a Third, and Higher ſenſe: <hi>As thy Days, ſo ſhall thy ſtrength be.</hi> Now, as his Shooes are of Iron and Braſs; ſo his Dayes are to be numbred, even in that Kingdom of Jeſus Chriſt, and that Kingdom of Eternity. There is therefore a ſtrength ſuitable to that State of Glory, of Eternal Glory and Salvation, in the Kingdom of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Conſider, Indeed it is a length of Duration be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond Expreſſion, beyond Comprehenſion. The thouſand years that the Scripture ſpeaks of, that the Kingdom of Chriſt ſhall be in viſible Glory; that is, fully taken care for, and the ſtate of Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity after that, or the ſtate of Eternity rather com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending that, and one with it: Of that Kingdom there ſhall be no end, for as the Day, or Days of Eternity, ſo their ſtrength ſhall be the ſtrength of Eternity. So in that vaſtneſs of Eternity, a Created Being that could not uphold and bear up it ſelf, it ſhall be born up by that Fountain of Life that is in God, and by that Great Mediator of Life, the Lord Jeſus Chriſt: He will take care, that even throughout Everlaſtings of Everlaſtings, there ſhall not be the leaſt Retraction, a retracting,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:48870:13"/> a drawing back of the Powers and Spirits of Life. As the Days of Eternity, ſo ſhall be the ſtrength of the Servants of God.</p>
               <p>O! how unſpeakable, how incomprehenſibly Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious is this, that God hath ordained for everlaſting every one of our Spirits! It is not a Life of fifty, ſixty, eighty, or a hundred Years, or any ſuch Time to live the Life of Senſe and Body.</p>
               <p>It is all nothing, how long ſoever it be. We ſay, 'twas a wonderful Providence that kept <hi>Methuſelah</hi> ſo long, to ſo great an Age, to reach almoſt to a thouſand Years. Alas! this is nothing, though it be very great; yet we ſhould think, if we lived hundreds of Years in this Life, how ſhould we do for the Supports of it, and for the Vigorous of it.</p>
               <p>But now our Days are for the Days of Eternity; but as our Days, ſo ſhall our ſtrength be. And God hath aſſured this to us, in the <hi>16th. Pſalm,</hi> laſt Verſe, <hi>Thou wilt ſhew me the path of life; in thy preſence is fulneſs of joy, and at thy right hand there are pleaſures for evermore:</hi> So that every way, take the Days of the Servants of God how we will, as are our Days, ſo ſhall be our ſtrength.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>I come to the third Thing I Propoſed, and that was, to Argue the Certainty of this; I ſay, to ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue the certainty of it, and it ſtands upon theſe two Conſiderations, which I ſhall very briefly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to you.</p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:48870:14"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> It ariſes from that Infinite ſtrength of the Love of God in Jeſus Chriſt made over to his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants. If he rides in his Excellency on the Sky; if he will undertake for us, if he will be our Refuge whoſe are the Everlaſting Arms; if they lye under, it is impoſſible notwithſtanding all Enemies, we ſhould fall, he will thruſt them utterly out: There ſhall be no power of Satan, there ſhall be no power of Sin, no pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Death, but whatſoever it be, it ſhall be ſhut out for ever in the Lake; He'll ſay, thruſt them out, and deſtroy them. If he, I ſay, undertake, how can it be otherwiſe; if he will ride in the Heaven for our ſake? We ſhould therefore often ſay to our ſelves, Let us conſider, in all the Jealouſies of our Natures, and of our weak Beings; in the midſt of all theſe, have we not an Eternal God? Have we not an Infinite and Omnipotent Being? If he take ſuch a Drop of Being as I am, this trembling Drop, and if he'll ſay, I'll encloſe this little Drop in my own Omnipotency, and ſet it in the Ocean of my own Immenſe Being, and I'll take care and ſecure it every moment. How ſafe are we! As we find in that Song God commanded to be ſung, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 27. 2, 3. <hi>In that day ſing ye unto her, A Vineyard of red Wine, I the Lord do keep it, I will water it every moment:</hi> I will keep it, and ſuſtain it from the firſt to the laſt; from the very beginning of the Creation to Eternity; and from Electing Love in Eternity, throughout Eternity of Ages. <hi>I the Lord will keep it, I will water it every moment, leſt any hurt it, I will keep it night and day:</hi> And ſo it ariſes from the Infiniteneſs of God, and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:48870:14"/> from that Unchangeableneſs, that he will never fail, that he will never take off his Help.</p>
               <p>And therefore God's ſtrength is our ſtrength, and God's Eternity is our Security, and the certainty of our ſtate of life. O! how excellent therefore is that in the <hi>40th.</hi> of <hi>Iſaiah, 27th.</hi> Verſe, <hi>Why ſayeſt thou, O Jacob, and ſpeakeſt O Iſrael, my way is hid from the Lord, and my Judgment is paſſed over from my God? Haſt thou not known, haſt thou not heard, that the everlaſting God, the Lord, the Creator of the ends of the Earth fainteth not, neither is weary, there is no ſearching of his underſtanding: He giveth power to the faint, and to them that have no might, he encreaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth ſtrength; even the Youths ſhall faint and he weary, and the Young men ſhall utterly fail: But they that wait upon the Lord ſhall renew their ſtrength, they ſhall mount up with wings as Eagles; they ſhall run, and not be wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, they ſhall walk, and not faint.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O! If we could read, and meditate, and unite, and Conſolidate ſuch a Scripture as this with our own Hearts, with what certainty might we ſay, As our Days, ſo ſhall our ſtrength be? Take them any way, as I have now deſcribed and Repreſented them to you: Becauſe the Creator of the ends of the Earth fainteth not, neither is weary; there is no ſearching of his Underſtanding. He giveth power to the faint, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And then in the ſecond place, it ariſes from that great Interpoſer betwixt God and us, the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, into whoſe hands he hath entruſted ſtrength, and laid help upon him, becauſe he is mighty.</p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:48870:15"/>
               <p>I am perſwaded, we are not able to ſpeak of the great Security that Jeſus Chriſt is, between the Eternal God, and ſuch Creatures as we are. We do not know it, we ſhall know it, but we do not yet know it; no one is able to expreſs it to us, as the thing it ſelf is. We are not able to Declare or Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs the thing plentifully, as the expreſſion is in <hi>Job.</hi> Plentifully as it is, it is rather a matter of Profeſſion to us, or a matter of Confeſſion of Faith, and we cannot tell how to ſay it otherwiſe: But Oh the Infinite value of it, the Infinite Security of it, that it holds God and all his Saints together, that they can never be Divorced, they never ſhall be ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
               <p>This I ſay, the Interpoſal of Chriſt, it is ſo faſt, ſo ſtable, ſo firm a thing, that all that can be ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of it, is not any way equal to it. All the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes, though they are never ſo wiſe and good, betwixt the Creator and the Creature; betwixt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Mind, and the Intellectual and Rational Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; though they are expreſs'd never ſo well in the main, and never ſo true; though men are never ſo Great and Wiſe in theſe Diſcourſes; they cannot come near the high ſenſe of the Expreſſions of our Lord in this Great Point, who hath Loved us, and Reconciled us, and in whom the Creature loſt in it ſelf is united Spiritually to God in him.</p>
               <p>Men do not enough conſider that Indiſſoluble Centre of Union our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who can never be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:48870:15"/> out of the Centre, and that all the Lines run and meet in him.</p>
               <p>To conſider this, and to underſtand this, I ſay, I do not know who is able to expreſs the thing as it is, to declare the thing plentifully as it it is. The Secret of this point of Wiſdom, I am fully aſſured is double; nay, a thouſand-fold to all we know, and to all we can ſpeak. It is ſumm'd up admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly in that <hi>17th.</hi> of <hi>John,</hi> that I have heretofore mentioned in ſuch Diſcourſes as theſe, and always I am ready to mention, it is ſo great: <hi>And I have declared unto them thy Name, and will declare it, that the love wherewith thou haſt loved me, may be in them, and I in them: I in them, and thou in me, that they may be made perfect in one, and that the World may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that thou haſt ſent me, and haſt loved them as thou haſt loved me.</hi> Ver. 24. <hi>Father I will, that they alſo whom thou haſt given me, be with me where I am, that they may behold my Glory which thou haſt given me; for thou lovedſt me before the foundation of the World: That they all may be one, as thou Father art in me, and I in thee, that they alſo may be one in us,</hi> &amp;c. Ver. 21. 23, 24, 26.</p>
               <p>Now in theſe things, the Union by Vertue of the Interpoſal of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, is ſo great, that I ſay, we do but quibble in compariſon; Men do but quibble, when they talk of Union between the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor and the Creature, except they conſider this great Intervention, the coming between of the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus. I doubt not, take the Holieſt Saint in Heaven,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:48870:16"/> if there were no Interpoſer between God and them, but they might be loſt, though they are in the preſent Happineſs and Bleſſedneſs of the Enjoyment of God. Here is the Lord Jeſus coming between, <hi>Father I will, that they alſo whom thou haſt given me, be with me where I am, that they may behold my Glory which thou haſt given me,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>This is our great Security, and this is that that makes our Shooes indeed to be Iron and Braſs, and that as our Day is, ſo our Strength ſhall be.</p>
               <p>I come therefore to the Laſt Particular, and that is, to ſhew that there muſt be a Time, when this ſhall be Triumphant: I ſay, there muſt be a Time of Glorious Appearance.</p>
               <p>For, the World dares Contradict this now, the World dares laugh at it; they dare to take upon them to ſay, This is nothing but Fancy, this is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but Talk, this is nothing but a high flight of Expreſſion; or (as they call it) a <hi>Cant,</hi> a High Cant of Talk, a high Enthuſiaſm, a heated Fancy; therefore, I ſay, there muſt be a Time, that ſhall out-face all theſe Taunts, that ſhall out-look them; for Scoffers can look againſt Saints now, and they can ſay, as they in <hi>Nehemiah</hi> ſaid, <hi>What will theſe pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull people do? what will theſe ſilly feeble folk do, to ſpeak of things at this rate?</hi> Do we not ſee how their Faith, and their Confidence ſtaggers at every turn? Are they not in fear? And does not their Faith ſink low? and are they not afraid to Dye? and are they not oftentimes under horror and trouble of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence? How can theſe things be?</p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:48870:16"/>
               <p>Now I ſay, notwithſtanding this, there is a hold of things, even now, that can never be turn'd off: There is a Conſibulation, as I may ſo call it; a Claſp of things, held by God and Jeſus Chriſt now, that can never be ſeparated; But it muſt come into a more Triumphant State; and it muſt come to that, that it muſt be viſible. And therefore, as I have often ſaid, there is a Thouſand years to make it ſo, wherein there ſhall be a mutual Aſpect of God on the Saints, and of the Saints on God, that ſhall be made viſible to all: And the Wicked ſhall grieve, and look on and wonder to ſee, and gnaſh their Teeth to ſee what a Union here is ſtruck and Conſolidated betwixt God and the Souls of his Saints through Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>It will be their Horror and Aſtoniſhment for ever: And therefore Chriſt ſpeaks in that <hi>17th.</hi> of <hi>John,</hi> I named to you before; that the World may believe: Believe as the Devils believe, and Tremble; they ſhall be forced <hi>to believe:</hi> ſaith our Lord, <hi>that the World may believe that thou haſt ſent me, and haſt loved them, as thou haſt loved me,</hi> (latter part of the <hi>21st.</hi> Verſe:) That the World may know it, and that the World may believe it: This is that which God will take care to ſhew, he'll magnifie himſelf by at that Day. Then ſhall all the Servants of God come out in their Shooes of Braſs and Iron, (as I may ſo expreſs it) and they ſhall tread down every thing that hath been an Enemy to them, they ſhall tread it down as the Mire of the ſtreet; they ſhall come out Armed, and trample the Nations in Anger, and Fury, for it is given to them, even as to Chriſt;
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:48870:17"/> they ſhall trample and Rule the Nations with a Rod of Iron. This Honour have all his Saints.</p>
               <p>This I ſpeak, (God knows) not for Language ſake, or for Expreſſion ſake, but what I am fully aſſured of, and what I have ſuch Evidence of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture for, that theſe things ſhall come into the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, moſt open, and manifeſt Appearance that can be: And then ſhall be fulfilled, what is written in the <hi>7th.</hi> of <hi>Micah, 16th.</hi> Verſe, <hi>The Nations ſhall ſee, and be confounded at their might; they ſhall lay their hand upon their mouth, their ears ſhall be deaf: They ſhall lick the duſt like a Serpent, they ſhall move out of their holes like Worms of the earth; they ſhall be afraid of the Lord our God, and ſhall fear becauſe of thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O! how great ſhall this State of Things be! I ſay, how great ſhall it be! And then ſaith he in the <hi>10th.</hi> Verſe, <hi>Then ſhe that is mine Enemy ſhall ſee it, and ſhame ſhall cover her which ſaid unto me, Where is the Lord thy God?</hi> You ſhall ſee (ſay the Enemies of Saints) all this that you talk of, what a dark Cloud it will ſet in.</p>
               <p>When the Servants of God come to be in Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and come to Dye, Why then ſayes the Enemy, where is the Lord thy God? Where are theſe Shooes of Iron and Braſs? where is this Strength according to the Day? where is the Lord thy God? Mine eyes ſhall behold her. I'll look upon them, I'll laugh at them, I'll ſcorn them, becauſe I ſee no ſuch thing. But ſaith the Spirit of God, <hi>Now ſhall they be trod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den down as the mire of the ſtreets.</hi> All the Enemies
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:48870:17"/> of God ſhall be trodden down as the mire of the ſtreets: And as <hi>David</hi> in the <hi>18th. Pſalm,</hi> expreſſes with what Courage and Power, and mighty Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs he went out againſt his Enemies; ſaith he, <hi>Then did I beat them ſmall as the duſt: and thou haſt given me the ſhield of thy Salvation, and thy right hand hath holden me up,</hi> (Ver. 35.) <hi>Thy gentleneſs hath make me great: Thou haſt enlarged my ſteps under me, that my feet did not ſlip.</hi> My Feet were ſhod with Iron and Braſs, that they did not ſlip.</p>
               <p>As you know Shooes of Iron and Braſs they keep ſteady and firm, not ſlippery. <hi>I have purſued mine Enemies, and overtaken them; neither did I turn again, till they were conſumed: I have wounded them, that they were not able to riſe, they are fallen under my feet.</hi> And ſo he goes on, expreſſing it, that <hi>he beat them ſmall, as the very Duſt before the wind, and there was none to ſave them.</hi> Ver. 22. <hi>And I caſt them out as the Dirt in the ſtreet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And if you ſay, But O! how ſhall this be to ſuch Sinners as we are? How can we look for ſuch a thing as this is? Do we not find that we are Men of the ſame Infirmities, of the ſame Paſſions, of the ſame Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions? Therefore <hi>Micah</hi> goes on, <hi>Micah</hi> 7. 18. <hi>Who is a God like unto thee, that pardoneth iniquity, and paſſeth by the tranſgreſſion of the remnant of his heritage? He retaineth not his anger for ever, becauſe he delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in mercy. He will turn again, he will have compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion upon us; he will ſubdue our iniquities, and thou wilt caſt all their ſins into the depth of the Sea. Thou wilt perform the truth to Jacob, and the mercy to Abraham, which thou haſt ſworn unto our Fathers from the days of old.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:48870:18"/>
               <p>Therefore let us all Encourage our ſelves that wait upon God: for we ſhall renew our ſtrength, let our caſe be never ſo dark and gloomy; let things be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo hard, yet the knor of Union that is faſtned be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt Chriſt and us, and ſo with God, it ſhall ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure us to hold out throughout Eternities of Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities.</p>
               <p>Let us therefore encourage our ſelves (in regard of every thing) in the Lord our God, and wait for that great ſtate of things that certainly is very near; That <hi>that Day,</hi> as it is often called in the Prophets: <hi>In that Day,</hi> and <hi>that Day.</hi> Now <hi>that Day,</hi> (as I may ſo expreſs it to you) it is very near.</p>
               <p>Let us therefore now Encourage our ſelves in the Lord our God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:48870:18"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
